RAHUL SHARMA

+91 9085289995 / 7999268061 ♦ Assam, IN

rsharma0374@gmail.com ♦ www.linkedin.com/in/rahul0374/ ♦ portfolio.guardianservices.in/rahulsharma

A motivated Java developer with 2.5+ years of experience in backend development seeking a challenging position where I can apply my Java programming skills and problem-solving abilities to contribute effectively towards building dynamic and resilient software solutions.

EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Developer

Dec 2023 - Current

Lentra

Pune, IN

Company Description: Lentra is a leading FinTech company specializing in advanced lending solutions, driving innovation in the financial sector with cutting-edge technology and data-driven insights.

- Successfully integrated a Privilege Card feature into the project, driving a 20% increase in customer engagement by offering targeted promotions and personalized offers.
- Successfully implemented Pennant Loan Management System (LMS), optimizing loan booking workflows and improving system efficiency.
- Led IDEARAS EStamping project development in Java. Developed cutting-edge solutions for effective electronic stamping operations. Utilized Java knowledge to design scalable and reliable systems for smooth project implementation and client satisfaction.
- Successfully integrated the NSDL API into our financial platform, enhancing data validation and streamlining transaction processes. This integration improved the accuracy and efficiency of our lending services, resulting in a 30% reduction in processing time.
- used multi-bureau credit reporting services in our platform to give suitable offers to the customer. This enhancement improved our risk evaluation accuracy by 25%, facilitating better lending decisions and reducing default rates.
- Led the integration of the eMandate API into our financial system, automating the electronic mandate process for recurring payments. This implementation enhanced user experience and reduced manual intervention by 40% improving transaction reliability.
- Integrated EPFO data as a surrogate metric into our lending platform to optimize offer personalization. This integration enabled more accurate assessments of financial stability, leading to tailored loan offers and a 20% increase in approval rates.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to develop and maintain microservices-based applications using Java and Spring Framework, ensuring high performance and scalability.
- Strong working knowledge of Database Programming using and maintaining NoSQL(MongoDB) Triggers and Stored Procedures.
- Expertise in Programming with Core Java Concepts multithreading, collections, and asynchronous programming.
- Used AWS as a cloud platform leveraging its services and EC2. Setting up databases in AWS using S3 bucket and configuring instance backups to S3 bucket.
- Used BurpSuite tool for penetration testing of APIs.

Software Developer

Lentra

Jan 2022 - Nov 2023

Pune, IN

- Have knowledge on NoSQL databases Mongo DB.
- Used Spring Web MVC framework.
- A result-driven, customer-focused and dedicated IT Professional with an approach to build quality application.

• Addressed and resolved VAPT (Vulnerability Assessment and Penetration Testing) points promptly, enhancing the security posture of the applications.

PROJECTS

Privilege Club Membership. Developed the "Privilege Club Membership" project in Java, integrating MongoDB database and APIs while incorporating encryption and decryption logic for enhanced data security.

Pennant Migration From LOS development to LMS integration. Streamlining data flow and improving interoperability between LOS and LMS. Implementing Java-based solutions for seamless communication and data exchange. Streamlining workflow and user experience.

KYC. Made contributions to the KYC (Know Your Customer) module, implementing strong data validation and verification procedures in order to improve compliance and reduce fraud.

Face Authentication. Implemented Face Authentication, adding advanced facial recognition technology to our apps, improving security and user experience.

CC bundling module. Played a pivotal role in the development and implementation of the CC bundling module, streamlining the distribution of credit cards to consumers, leading to a remarkable 30% growth in business operations and a substantial 20% reduction in processing time.

Lead generation project. Developed Java-based lead generation & in-store use cases such as self-service capabilities, DAP (Digital Asset Platforms) and HL BRE (Home Loan) to improve operational performance and customer engagement.

RESPONSIBILITIES

- Involved in various phases of Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC) as requirement gathering, data modeling, analysis, architecture design & development for the project.
- Involved in the discussions with business users, and the testing team to finalize the technical design documents and story point allocation for user stories.
- Designed Restful request and response to be used in the project.
- Used IntelliJ and Tomcat as web servers for deploying the application.
- Performed User Interface Design and coding using Java, and Spring framework.
- Helped the production support team to solve trouble reports.

SKILLS

Technical Skills Java, Spring, Angular, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, MongoDB, AWS, GIT, MicroSer-

vice, REST Service, Oracle OCI

Soft Skills Problem-solving, Attention to detail, Adaptability, Teamwork, Critical thinking,

and Continuous learning.

Development Tools IntelliJ IDEA, VS Code, NosqlBooster, Postman, BurpSuite, SonarQube.

Language Assamese, Bengali, English, Hindi.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Engineering, LNCTE, Bhopal, MP

2016 - 2020

ACHIEVEMENTS AND CERTIFICATIONS

- Successfully completed the MongoDB Developer and Administrator course.
- Successfully completed Cybersecurity Awareness Program.
- Received the SPOT AWARD for outstanding effort and contribution in Client Delivery FY 22-23.
- Received the EXTRA MILLER AWARD for outstanding effort and contribution in Client Delivery FY 23-24.